Introduction to XML

What is XML?
XML stands for EXtensible Markup Language
XML is a markup language much like HTML.
XML was designed to describe data.
XML tags are not predefined in XML. You must define your own tags.
XML is self describing.
XML uses a DTD (Document Type Definition) to formally describe the data.
----------------------------------------------
The main difference between XML and HTML
- XML is not a replacement for HTML. XML and HTML were designed with different goals:
- XML was designed to describe data and to focus on what data is. HTML was designed to display data and to focus on how data looks.
- HTML is about displaying information, XML is about describing information.
------------------------
XML is extensible
The tags used to markup HTML documents and the structure of HTML documents are predefined. The author of HTML documents can only use tags that are defined in the HTML standard.

XML allows the author to define his own tags and his own document structure.
-------------------------------
XML is a complement to HTML
It is important to understand that XML is not a replacement for HTML. In the future development of the Web it is most likely that XML will be used to structure and describe the Web data, while HTML will be used to format and display the same data.
-------------------------------
XML in future Web development
We have been participating in XML development since its creation. It has been amazing to see how quickly the XML standard has been developed, and how quickly a large number of software vendors have adopted the standard.

We strongly believe that XML will be as important to the future of the Web as HTML has been to the foundation of the Web. XML is the future for all data transmission and data manipulation over the Web.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
How can XML be used?
XML can keep data separated from your HTML
XML can be used to store data inside HTML documents
XML can be used as a format to exchange information
XML can be used to store data in files or in databases
---------------------------------------------
XML can keep data separated from your HTML
HTML pages are used to display data. Data is often stored inside HTML pages. With XML this data can now be stored in a separate XML file. This way you can concentrate on using HTML for formatting and display, and be sure that changes in the underlying data will not force changes to any of your HTML code.
------------------------------------------------
XML can also store data inside HTML documents
XML data can also be stored inside HTML pages as “Data Islands”. You can still concentrate on using HTML for formatting and displaying the data.
-------------------------------------
XML can be used to exchange data
In the real world, computer systems and databases contain data in incompatible formats. One of the
most time consuming challenges for developers has been to exchange data between such systems over the Internet. Converting the data to XML can greatly reduce this complexity and create data that can be read by different types of applications.
--------------------------------
XML can be used to store data
XML can also be used to store data in files or in databases. Applications can be written to store and retrieve information from the store, and generic applications can be used to display the data.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
XML Syntax

An example XML document:
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<note>
<to>Tove</to>
<from>Jani</from>
<heading>Reminder</heading>
<body>Don't forget me this weekend!</body>
</note>

The first line in the document: The XML declaration should always be included. It defines the XML version of the document. In this case the document conforms to the 1.0 specification of XML:
<?xml version="1.0"?>

The next line defines the first element of the document (the root element):
<note>

The next lines defines 4 child elements of the root (to, from, heading, and
body):
<to>Tove</to>
<from>Jani</from>
<heading>Reminder</heading>
<body>Don't forget me this weekend!</body>

The last line defines the end of the root element:
</note>
--------------------------------------------- 
All XML elements must have a closing tag

In HTML some elements do not have to have a closing tag. The following code is legal in HTML:

<p>This is a paragraph
<p>This is another paragraph
In XML all elements must have a closing tag like this:

<p>This is a paragraph</p>
<p>This is another paragraph</p>
------------------------------- 
XML tags are case sensitive

XML tags are case sensitive. The tag <Letter> is different from the tag <letter>.

Opening and closing tags must therefore be written with the same case:

<Message>This is incorrect</message>
 
<message>This is correct</message>
-------------------------------------------- 
All XML elements must be properly nested

In HTML some elements can be improperly nested within each other like this:

<b><i>This text is bold and italic</b></i>
In XML all elements must be properly nested within each other like this

<b><i>This text is bold and italic</i></b>
------------------------------------------ 
All XML documents must have a root tag

All XML documents must contain a single tag pair to define the root element. All other elements must be nested within the root element. All elements can have sub (children) elements. Sub elements must be in pairs and correctly nested within their parent element:

<root>
  <child>
    <subchild>
    </subchild>
  </child>
</root>
--------------------------------------------- 
Attribute values must always be quoted

XML elements can have attributes in name/value pairs just like in HTML. In XML the attribute value must always be quoted. Study the two XML documents below. The first one is incorrect, the second is correct:

<?xml version="1.0"?>
<note date=12/11/99>
<to>Tove</to>
<from>Jani</from>
<heading>Reminder</heading>
<body>Don't forget me this weekend!</body>
</note>
 

<?xml version="1.0"?>
<note date="12/11/99">
<to>Tove</to>
<from>Jani</from>
<heading>Reminder</heading>
<body>Don't forget me this weekend!</body>
</note>
---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
XML Attributes

XML attributes are normally used to describe XML elements, or to provide additional information about elements. From HTML you can remember this construct: <IMG SRC=”computer.gif”>. In this HTML example SRC is an attribute to the IMG element. The SRC attribute provides additional information about the element.

Attributes are always contained within the start tag of an element. Here are some examples:

HTML examples:
<img src="computer.gif">
<a href="demo.asp">

XML examples:
<file type="gif">
<person id="3344">

Usually, or most common, attributes are used to provide information that is not a part of the content of the XML document. Did you understand that? Here is another way to express that: Often attribute data is more important to the XML parser than to the reader. Did you understand it now? Anyway, in the example above, the person id is a counter value that is irrelevant to the reader, but important to software that wants to manipulate the person element.
-----------------------------------------
Use of Elements vs. Attributes

Take a look at these examples:

Using an Attribute for sex:

<person sex="female">
  <firstname>Anna</firstname>
  <lastname>Smith</lastname>
</person>

Using an Element for sex:

<person>
  <sex>female</sex>
  <firstname>Anna</firstname>
  <lastname>Smith</lastname>
</person>

In the first example sex is an attribute. In the last example sex is an element. Both examples provides the same information to the reader.

There are no fixed rules about when to use attributes to describe data, and when to use elements. My experience is however; that attributes are handy in HTML, but in XML you should try to avoid them, as long as the same information can be expressed using elements.

Here is another example, demonstrating how elements can be used instead of attributes. The following three XML documents contain exactly the same information. A date attribute is used in the first, a date element is used in the second, and an expanded date element is used in the third:

<?xml version="1.0"?>
<note date="12/11/99">
<to>Tove</to>
<from>Jani</from>
<heading>Reminder</heading>
<body>Don't forget me this weekend!</body>
</note>

<?xml version="1.0"?>
<note>
<date>12/11/99</date>
<to>Tove</to>
<from>Jani</from>
<heading>Reminder</heading>
<body>Don't forget me this weekend!</body>
</note>

<?xml version="1.0"?>
<note>
<date>
  <day>12</day>
  <month>11</month>
  <year>99</year>
</date>
<to>Tove</to>
<from>Jani</from>
<heading>Reminder</heading>
<body>Don't forget me this weekend!</body>
</note>
------------------------------------------ 
Avoid using attributes? (I say yes!)

Why should you avoid using attributes? Should you just take my word for it? These are some of the problems using attributes:

attributes can not contain multiple values (elements can)
attributes are not expandable (for future changes)
attributes can not describe structures (like child elements can)
attributes are more difficult to manipulate by program code
attribute values are not easy to test against a DTD

If you start using attributes as containers for XML data, you might end up with documents that are both difficult to maintain and to manipulate. What I’m trying to say is that you should use elements to describe your data. Use attributes only to provide information that is not relevant to the reader. Please don’t end up like this:

<?xml version="1.0"?>
<note day="12" month="11" year="99"
to="Tove" from="Jani" heading="Reminder"
body="Don't forget me this weekend!">
</note>

This don’t look much like XML. Got the point?
------------------------------------------
An Exception to my Attribute rule

Rules always have exceptions. My rule about not using attributes has one too:

Sometimes I assign ID references to elements in my XML documents. These ID references can be used to access XML element in much the same way as the NAME or ID attributes in HTML. This example demonstrates this:

<?xml version="1.0"?>
<messages>
  <note ID="501">
    <to>Tove</to>
    <from>Jani</from>
    <heading>Reminder</heading>
    <body>Don't forget me this weekend!</body>
  </note>

  <note ID="502">
    <to>Jani</to>
    <from>Tove</from>
    <heading>Re: Reminder</heading>
    <body>I will not!</body>
  </note> 
</messages>
The ID in these examples is just a counter, or a unique identifier, to identify the different notes in the XML file.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
Introduction to DTD

The purpose of a DTD is to define the legal building blocks of an XML document. It defines the document structure with a list of legal elements. A DTD can be declared inline in your XML document, or as an external reference.
--------------------
Internal DTD

This is an XML document with a Document Type Definition: (Open
it in IE5, and select view source)

<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE note [
  <!ELEMENT note    (to,from,heading,body)>
  <!ELEMENT to      (#PCDATA)>
  <!ELEMENT from    (#PCDATA)>
  <!ELEMENT heading (#PCDATA)>
  <!ELEMENT body    (#PCDATA)>
]>
<note>
<to>Tove</to>
<from>Jani</from>
<heading>Reminder</heading>
<body>Don't forget me this weekend!</body>
</note>

The DTD is interpreted like this:
!ELEMENT note (in line 2) defines the element “note” as having
four elements: “to,from,heading,body”.
!ELEMENT to (in line 3) defines the “to” element  to be of
the type “CDATA”.
!ELEMENT from (in line 4) defines the “from” element to be of the
type “CDATA”
and so on…..
-----------------
External DTD

This is the same XML document with an external DTD:  (Open
it in IE5, and select view source)

<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE note SYSTEM "note.dtd">
<note>
<to>Tove</to>
<from>Jani</from>
<heading>Reminder</heading>
<body>Don't forget me this weekend!</body>
</note>

This is a copy of the file “note.dtd” containing the Document

Type Definition:

<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!ELEMENT note (to,from,heading,body)>
<!ELEMENT to (#PCDATA)>
<!ELEMENT from (#PCDATA)>
<!ELEMENT heading (#PCDATA)>
<!ELEMENT body (#PCDATA)>
----------------------
Why use a DTD?

XML provides an application independent way of sharing data. With a DTD, independent groups of people can agree to use a common DTD for interchanging data. Your application can use a standard DTD to verify that data that you receive from the outside world is valid. You can also use a DTD to verify your own data.

A lot of forums are emerging to define standard DTDs for almost everything in the areas of data exchange. Take a look at: CommerceNet’s XML exchange and http://www.schema.net.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
DTD – Elements

Declaring an Element

In the DTD, XML elements are declared with an element declaration. An element declaration has the following syntax:

<!ELEMENT element-name (element-content)>
----------------------
Empty elements

Empty elements are declared with the keyword EMPTY inside the parentheses:

<!ELEMENT element-name (EMPTY)>

example:
<!ELEMENT img (EMPTY)>
------------------------- 
Elements with data

Elements with data are declared with the data type inside parentheses:

<!ELEMENT element-name (#CDATA)>
or
<!ELEMENT element-name (#PCDATA)>
or
<!ELEMENT element-name (ANY)>
example:
<!ELEMENT note (#PCDATA)>
 

#CDATA means the element contains character data that is not supposed to be parsed by a parser.
#PCDATA means that the element contains data that IS going to be parsed by a parser.
The keyword ANY declares an element with any content.

If a #PCDATA section contains elements, these elements must also be declared.
----------------------------------------
Elements with children (sequences)

Elements with one or more children are defined with the name of the children elements inside
the parentheses:

<!ELEMENT element-name (child-element-name)>
or
<!ELEMENT element-name (child-element-name,child-element-name,.....)>
example:
<!ELEMENT note (to,from,heading,body)>
 

When children are declared in a sequence separated by commas, the children must appear in the same sequence in the document. In a full declaration, the children must also be declared, and the children can also have children.
The full declaration of the note document will be:

<!ELEMENT note (to,from,heading,body)>
<!ELEMENT to      (#CDATA)>
<!ELEMENT from    (#CDATA)>
<!ELEMENT heading (#CDATA)>
<!ELEMENT body    (#CDATA)>
----------------- 
Wrapping

If the DTD is to be included in your XML source file, it should be wrapped in a DOCTYPE definition with the following syntax:

<!DOCTYPE root-element [element-declarations]>
example:
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE note [
  <!ELEMENT note (to,from,heading,body)>
  <!ELEMENT to      (#CDATA)>
  <!ELEMENT from    (#CDATA)>
  <!ELEMENT heading (#CDATA)>
  <!ELEMENT body    (#CDATA)>
]>
<note>
  <to>Tove</to>
  <from>Jani</from>
  <heading>Reminder</heading>
  <body>Don't forget me this weekend</body>
</note>
---------------------------------------------------------- 
Declaring only one occurrence of the same element

<!ELEMENT element-name (child-name)>
example
<!ELEMENT note (message)>
The example declaration above declares that the child element message can only occur one time inside the note element.
---------------------------------------------------------
Declaring minimum one occurrence of the same element
<!ELEMENT element-name (child-name+)>
example
<!ELEMENT note (message+)>
The + sign in the example above declares that the child element message must occur one or more times inside the note element.
-----------------------------------------------------------------
Declaring zero or more occurrences of the same element
<!ELEMENT element-name (child-name*)>
example
<!ELEMENT note (message*)>
The * sign in the example above declares that the child element message can occur zero or more times inside the note element.
---------------------------------------------------------
Declaring zero or one occurrences of the same element
<!ELEMENT element-name (child-name?)>
example
<!ELEMENT note (message?)>
The ? sign in the example above declares that the child element message can occur zero or one times inside the note element.
---------------------------
Declaring mixed content
example
<!ELEMENT note (to+,from,header,message*,#PCDATA)>
The example above declares that the element note must contain at least one to child element, exactly one from child element, exactly one header, zero or more message, and some other parsed character data as well. Puh!
---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
DTD – Attributes

Declaring Attributes

In the DTD, XML element attributes are declared with an ATTLIST declaration. An attribute declaration has the following syntax:

<!ATTLIST element-name attribute-name attribute-type default-value>

As you can see from the syntax above, the ATTLIST declaration defines the element which can have the attribute, the name of the attribute, the type of the attribute, and the default attribute value.

The attribute-type can have the following values:

VALUE		EXPLANATION
CDATA		The value is character data
(eval|eval|..)  The value must be an enumerated value
ID		The value is an unique id
IDREF		The value is the id of another element
IDREFS		The value is a list of other ids
NMTOKEN		The value is a valid XML name
NMTOKENS	The value is a list of valid XML names
ENTITY		The value is an entity
ENTITIES	The value is a list of entities
NOTATION	The value is a name of a notation
xml:		The value is predefined

The attribute-default-value can have the following values:

VALUE		EXPLANATION
#DEFAULT value	The attribute has a default value
#REQUIRED	The attribute value must be included in the element
#IMPLIED	The attribute does not have to be included
#FIXED value	The attribute value is fixed
-----------------------------------
Attribute declaration example
DTD example:
<!ELEMENT square EMPTY>
  <!ATTLIST square width CDATA "0">

XML example:
<square width="100"></square>
In the above example the element square is defined to be an empty element with the attributes width of  type CDATA. The width attribute has a default value of 0.
--------------------------------
Default attribute value
Syntax:
<!ATTLIST element-name attribute-name CDATA "default-value">

DTD example:
<!ATTLIST payment type CDATA "check">

XML example:
<payment type="check">
 

Specifying a default value for an attribute, assures that the attribute will get a value even if the author of the XML document didn’t include it.
-------------------------------
Implied attribute
Syntax:
<!ATTLIST element-name attribute-name attribute-type #IMPLIED>
DTD example:
<!ATTLIST contact fax CDATA #IMPLIED>

XML example:
<contact fax="555-667788">
 

Use an implied attribute if you don’t want to force the author to include an attribute and you don’t have an option for a default value either.
-------------------------
Required attribute
Syntax:
<!ATTLIST element-name attribute_name attribute-type #REQUIRED>
DTD example:
<!ATTLIST person number CDATA #REQUIRED>

XML example:
<person number="5677">
 

Use a required attribute if you don’t have an option for a default value, but still want to force the attribute to be present.
-----------------------------
Fixed attribute value
Syntax:
<!ATTLIST element-name attribute-name attribute-type #FIXED "value">
DTD example:
<!ATTLIST sender company CDATA #FIXED "Microsoft">


XML example:
<sender company="Microsoft">
 

Use a fixed attribute value when you want an attribute to have a fixed value without allowing the author to change it. If an author includes another value, the XML parser will return an error.
------------------------------------
Enumerated attribute values
Syntax:
<!ATTLIST element-name attribute-name (eval|eval|..) default-value>
DTD example:
<!ATTLIST payment type (check|cash) "cash">

XML example:
<payment type="check">
or
<payment type="cash">
 

Use enumerated attribute values when you want the attribute values to be one of a fixed set of legal values.
---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
DTD – Entities

Entities:
Entities as variables used to define shortcuts to common text.
Entity references are references to entities.
Entities can be declared internal.
Entities can be declared external
----------------------------------
Internal Entity Declaration

Syntax:
<!ENTITY entity-name "entity-value">

DTD Example:
<!ENTITY writer "Jan Egil Refsnes.">
<!ENTITY copyright "Copyright XML101.">
XML example:
<author>&writer;&copyright;</author>
-----------------------------
External Entity Declaration

Syntax:
<!ENTITY entity-name SYSTEM "URI/URL">

DTD Example:
<!ENTITY writer    SYSTEM "http://www.xml101.com/entities/entities.xml">
<!ENTITY copyright SYSTEM "http://www.xml101.com/entities/entities.dtd">
XML example:
<author>&writer;&copyright;</author>
---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
DTD Validation

Validating with the XML Parser
If you try to open an XML document, the XML Parser might generate an error. By accessing the parseError object, the exact error code, the error text, and even the line that caused the error can be retrieved:

var xmlDoc = new ActiveXObject("Microsoft.XMLDOM")
xmlDoc.async="false"
xmlDoc.validateOnParse="true"
xmlDoc.load("note_dtd_error.xml")

document.write("<br>Error Code: ")
document.write(xmlDoc.parseError.errorCode)
document.write("<br>Error Reason: ")
document.write(xmlDoc.parseError.reason)
document.write("<br>Error Line: ")
document.write(xmlDoc.parseError.line)
Try it Yourself or or just look at the XML file
--------------------------------
Turning Validation off
Validation can be turned off by setting the XML parser’s validateOnParse=”false”.

var xmlDoc = new ActiveXObject("Microsoft.XMLDOM")
xmlDoc.async="false"
xmlDoc.validateOnParse="false"
xmlDoc.load("note_dtd_error.xml")

document.write("<br>Error Code: ")
document.write(xmlDoc.parseError.errorCode)
document.write("<br>Error Reason: ")
document.write(xmlDoc.parseError.reason)
document.write("<br>Error Line: ")
document.write(xmlDoc.parseError.line)
---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
XML Schema

An XML Schema describes the structure of an XML document, just like a DTD.
An XML document with correct syntax is called "Well Formed".
An XML document validated against an XML Schema is both "Well Formed" and "Valid".
------------------
XML Schema

XML Schema is an XML-based alternative to DTD:

<xs:element name="note">
<xs:complexType>
  <xs:sequence>
    <xs:element name="to" type="xs:string"/>
    <xs:element name="from" type="xs:string"/>
    <xs:element name="heading" type="xs:string"/>
    <xs:element name="body" type="xs:string"/>
  </xs:sequence>
</xs:complexType>
</xs:element>

The Schema above is interpreted like this:
<xs:element name="note"> defines the element called "note"
<xs:complexType> the "note" element is a complex type
<xs:sequence> the complex type is a sequence of elements
<xs:element name="to" type="xs:string"> the element "to" is of type string (text)
<xs:element name="from" type="xs:string"> the element "from" is of type string
<xs:element name="heading" type="xs:string"> the element "heading" is of type string
<xs:element name="body" type="xs:string"> the element "body" is of type string
------------------------------------------
XML Schemas are More Powerful than DTD

XML Schemas are written in XML
XML Schemas are extensible to additions
XML Schemas support data types
XML Schemas support namespaces
-------------------------------
Why Use an XML Schema?

With XML Schema, your XML files can carry a description of its own format.
With XML Schema, independent groups of people can agree on a standard for interchanging data.
With XML Schema, you can verify data.
-------------------------------------
XML Schemas Support Data Types

One of the greatest strengths of XML Schemas is the support for data types:
It is easier to describe document content
It is easier to define restrictions on data
It is easier to validate the correctness of data
It is easier to convert data between different data types
----------------------------
XML Schemas use XML Syntax

Another great strength about XML Schemas is that they are written in XML:
You don't have to learn a new language
You can use your XML editor to edit your Schema files
You can use your XML parser to parse your Schema files
You can manipulate your Schemas with the XML DOM
You can transform your Schemas with XSLT
---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
The XML DOM

The Document Object Model
The DOM is a programming interface for HTML and XML documents. It defines the way a document can be accessed and manipulated.

Using a DOM, a programmer can create a document, navigate its structure, and add, modify, or delete its elements.

As a W3C specification, one important objective for the DOM has been to provide a standard programming interface that can be used in a wide variety of environments and applications.

The W3C DOM has been
designed to be used with any programming language.
----------------------------
The Node Interface
As you will se in the next section, a program called an XML parser can be used to load
an XML document into the memory of your computer. When the document is loaded, it’s information can be
retrieved and manipulated by accessing the Document Object Model (DOM).

The DOM represents a tree view of the XML document. The documentElement is the top-level of the tree. This element has one or many childNodes that represent the branches of the tree.

A Node Interface is used to read and write (or access if you like) the individual elements in the XML node tree. The childNodes property of the documentElement can be accesses with a for/each construct to enumerate each individual node.

The Microsoft XML parser used to demonstrate the DOM in this Web, supports all the necessary functions to traverse the node tree, access the nodes and their attribute values, insert and delete nodes, and convert the node tree back to XML.

All the demonstrated Microsoft XML parser functions are from the official W3C XML DOM recommendation, apart from the load and loadXML functions. (Believe it or not: The official DOM does not include standard functions for loading XML documents
!!)

A total of 13 node types are currently supported by the Microsoft XML parser. The following table lists the most commonly used node types:

NODE TYPE			EXAMPLE
Document type			<!DOCTYPE food SYSTEM “food.dtd”>
Processing instruction		<?xml version=”1.0″?>
Element				<drink type=”beer”>Carlsberg</drink>
Attribute			type=”beer”
Text				Carlsberg
---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
